so now we're going to talk about the application layer and up to now we've
been talking about these bottom layers and we've been sort of working our way
up we talked about the link layer the IP layer and the TCP layer and and and each
of these layers works with the other the the IP layer depends on the link layer
the TCP layer depends on and adds value to the IP layer and now we're going to
talk about the application layer that is going to make use of the services of the
TCP layer and the services of the TCP layer are basically to give us a
reliable sequenced end-to-end stream that can start in one application in one
computer and end in an application in a different computer and have a two-way
communication so I can send the word hello hello from one application and
then all kinds of billions of dollars of hardware hundreds of thousands of
engineers forty years of engineering design and out comes hello on the other
end and what's beautiful and this is the beauty of the layer of the four layer
architecture is we just pretend this is magic this is magic we send something
and out it comes with that magic available with that billions of dollars
and forty years of research magic available now what would we do right now
what would we do with that magic if we had it available to us so TCP is giving
us this reliable pipe we're gonna think about now we're gonna ignore all the
rest of it right we're gonna ignore all this part we're gonna put all we're gonna
say is we have an application on this into our computer now remember this is
your computer and say this is the server right so this is you and this is the
server and all the software runs in it in in every all the software is running
in your computer and all the software is running in the server so the question is
what are we going to do between these two things okay what how we what how are
we going to ask for data and this application is the client application and
this application is the server application client and server are not
necessarily the same very much the same client server are likely very different
applications the client is like give me information and the server is
responsible for giving the giving the information to the client so the client
is often making a request and then the server is making a response back and so
this client server mechanism this application to application communication
we can build a mail system with it worldwide web or we can stream videos
much like we'd be streaming this lecture back and forth we're going to focus on
the worldwide web because it's really simple and really elegant and it's part
of the easiest one to understand and it's the most popular but there are many
other protocols going on file transfer and others but the worldwide web
protocol HTTP D is the protocol that is the most popular so the there are two
basic questions that the application layer has to solve one is which
application gets the data and this is done using a mechanism called ports and
ports allow a IP address or a single computer or a single server to serve up
multiple services and then for a client to be able to dial up much like a
telephone extension and pick the service that they're interested in once you've
connected to the service that you're interested in like the worldwide web
service then you have to know the protocol to talk to that ports and TCP
are like a telephone extension number again meant like I said they you can
connect to an IP address but then you can connect to a port within it and so
if you think about a telephone number and an extension it's sort of a further
refinement an IP address gives us a particular server a piece of hardware
connected to the internet and then a port within that tells us what application
we're going to talk to so let's talk about ports and connections so if I have
a server and this is kind of an arbitrary server here's here is a single
server www.umich.edu and it has one IP address connected into the cloud we can
have many clients talking to it and we have many services running on this
server like sending email or logging into that server or retrieving web pages
or retrieving my mail from that server and there are ports so incoming email is
done generally in port 25 remote login is 22 or 23 web servers depending on
whether secure or not or 80 or 443 and the personal mailbox is on ports 109 or
110 and so these computers don't just connect to an IP address but they
connect to a port within an IP address so some common TCP ports that we have
are the ones I just mentioned and you can take a look at these on the internet
the various ports okay now once we have a connection to the web server or to the
mail server or to the post office server we have to know how to talk to it and
that's what's called an application protocol and that is the rules for
conversation the rules for conversing so TCP gives us this reliable connection we
now can connect to the server that we desire to connect to by using ports and
the question is what are we going to say across that connection and what we say
across that connection who talks first what do you send what comes back depends
on the kind of server that you're talking to we're going to play mostly
with the world what the world wide web click the wrong button there the world
wide web server because it's the simplest and it's the most obvious as to
what's going on so the world wide web clients and the worldwide which are
otherwise known as browsers the world wide web clients and the world wide web
servers communicate using a protocol called HTTP as a matter of fact if you
look at the top of your URL it's HTTP colon slash slash something that adopt
right and and so basically there is a specification for how this is done so
when they wrote down I'm gonna write the first web browser in the first web
server they also wrote a document about how that piece of software would talk to
this other piece of software and the and it's a very simple concept HTTP has a
protocol where you make a connection to the from the client to the server the
client requests the document the server feeds out the document and then the
connection is dropped okay so it's very simple we'll actually simulate this this
is called the HTTP request response cycle okay and so the way it works is
you're in a browser and you click on a link the browser is an application it's
the client running on your computer so so this is kind of your computer down
here okay you click on a link then the browser makes a connection to the web
server and sends a request to for the document the web server looks up does
whatever and sends the document back and then the document is displayed on your
screen okay so let me show you sort of how this works with a web browser so here
is a canonical web page so here's a browser here's the URL that I went and
got you can get this URL as well you can even look at the source so if you look
at this source there is my HTML but one of the things that's in this source is
a link and if I hover over top of this link it's gonna look like that to hover
over top of link you can see at the bottom of my screen you can see it's
going to tell you that we're about to go retrieve page two dot HTML now this
browser is running on my laptop it is a web client it is an HTTP client and I'm
about to click on this piece of software running on my computer and then it is
going to make a connection out the back of it retrieve a document and then show
me the other document so it's going to happen real fast I click on second page
it requested and got a document back and showed me the document so that's the
contents of the second document okay and so that is the request response cycle
that is triggered that is triggered by me making a click somewhere in my
browser the browser sees the click it opens a connection this is sort of the
internet over here it makes a connection request a document the document comes
back and then the new document is displayed the request response cycle
click request response display click request response display so let's take a
look in some more detail as to what's really going on here so the command that
is being sent up to the server across this connection remember this part here
is the internet right there the command is a get command and the document is
based on the URL I clicked on that the browser knows about and says get slash
page two dot HTML and then what comes back is HTML and that is a markup
language that describes how this doc this page is supposed to be shown so
let's say that we wanted some more detail on how this really worked right
let's say we want to write a web browser and we want to be a good citizen and we
want to talk properly to the the web well we would go back to the IETF the
Internet Engineering Task Force and we would go grab the document that says hey
if you want to write a browser this is what you do this is what you do if you
want to write a browser go grab RFC 1945 which is the hypertext transport
protocol version 1.0 now I'm sure there's more complex superseded versions
of it but if we read it and read it and read it we spent a lot of time we get
down to section 5.1.2 and I would say if you are making a request for a
document this is the request line it has the letters get followed by a space
followed by the URL you're looking for followed by a space followed by the
version okay so that is the rule that is what you're supposed to send down this
connection I'm gonna give us some more examples on page 24 and so we could read
all this and we could write a web browser but what we're gonna do is we're
gonna fake being a web browser we're gonna cheat we're gonna hack it we're
gonna pretend to be a web browser we're gonna send the commands to the web
browser now I'm gonna do this on a Macintosh you could also do it on
Windows if you install a telnet client okay so the key is you install a telnet
client now most people would say telnet is insecure and it is it's a very old
protocol because all it does is it opens a TCP connection to a host on a port
that I specify and whatever I type goes across that TCP connection so it's a
great way to hack especially older less secure protocols so because HTTP is
generally a public protocol it's not really highly protected so it's much
simpler to hack it hacking secure protocols is requires writing software
rather than typing commands so if you're on Windows you have to install telnet
telnet so what I'm going to show you in a second is I'm gonna show you hacking
and I'm gonna telnet to www.doctorchuck.com port 80 what I'm saying is
connect me to this server on the internet and connect me to port 80
because I want to do HTTP connections and then I will send one command I'm gonna
send that command and then the web server will give me back the page okay
it's probably easier for me to just do it so let's take a look I am going to
simulate what the web browser does when it's requesting well actually you will
go to the second page and when it's requesting the first page it's doing a
get for page one okay so that's what we're going to do except now we are
going to do it in a terminal so I'm gonna type telnet oops I was type this
wrong telnet www.doctor-chuck.com port 80 okay so now I am connected to the web
server on www.doctor-chuck.com I could for example type yo what is up
dude now that would suggest I have not read the protocol specification for the
HTTP protocol so I do not know that I'm supposed to type the word get here I'm
gonna type yo what is up dude and it goes you are not from my country you are not
from my planet I do not know what you said of course that the way web servers
are saying this is they're saying bad request your browser sent a request that
this server could not understand it is the request header is missing a colon
separator you do not comply go away but we did talk it just told us that whatever
we were saying is gibberish to it and that's okay because we have read the
document and so we can do it so let's do it so now I'm going to do a telnet to
dr.chuck.com on port 80 go to dr. chuck hook on to port 80 so we can talk to the
web server and now I am going to behave I read the specification I'm gonna type
GT get space one space HTTP colon slash slash www.doctor-chuck.com slash page
one dot HTM HTTP space one dot I think there's a slash there oh no no no get
right to be right slash 1.0 I think I got that right so that is what I'm supposed
to type if I am a real browser now I have to actually type another new line
so I'll type another new line and now whoa oh I gave it the wrong page look
look look look look look I wanted to do I told it to get page shut HTML so let's
do it again do it again I'm not very good at this my browser is much better
at it so I type get HTTP colon slash slash www.doctor-chuck.com slash page one
dot HTM space HTTP slash 1.0 I believe that's it let's hope I got it right
this time and then another enter and another enter yay I got it so this time
I type you know I type this then I type this now it gave me some header
information it's saying things like 200 okay means I like you what the time is
when this file was last modified it's an HTML file and it actually shows me the
HTML text and so we have just hacked a web server you can do this to like
facebook.com and do a get if you get the right thing it'll give you stuff you
could go to various sites you can fake browsers now you're only going to get so
far because at some point these servers know that you're not a browser because a
browser actually sends a little more stuff than what we just sent but you get
the picture okay it's a protocol where we have rules and if we type the right
thing if we type the right thing we know what the specification tells us to type
we are rewarded with the information on that server if we comply with the
server's request we can talk to it we know how to talk that we know what port
to talk to and we know I know what protocol to talk to that port we can
write a client that meets the needs of that server and extract the data so this
is I like I like command lines I like sort of old-school user interfaces and
this is a scene from one of the matrix movies that you may recall I can't put it
in here because of copyright requirements I might have the URL or
maybe students will come up with the URL you can probably search for the Trinity
hacking scene people put it up and then it gets taken down and someone else puts
it up so let me tell you a little story about this scene this scene was actually
written by a former student of mine who worked on all three matrix movies doing
IT work on the movies and they were in Australia shooting the the three the
second set of three movies and he saw this scene and the scene was supposed to
use a minority report style way for her to hack into the the power grid and shut
it down he said that's not the way that you hack into computers all good hackers
use a text-based interface interface some old thing and that's a throwback
interface so the Wachowski brothers told him rewrite it so we actually downloaded
the exact hacking software it's called n map which stands for network map it is
mapping the ports it's probes the ports and sees what's on the ports see what
version of the software is on each of the ports figures out what the what the
weaknesses of those things are and even automatically exploits the weaknesses so
he wrote a script that downloaded this thing that automatically breaks into
computers by the way the good guys use this and the bad guys use this same
thing the good guys use it to test all the computers on their campus and make
sure that they're okay and the bad guys used to break into the ones that the
good guys aren't smart enough to fix and so this was kind of cool and and the
people who wrote n map were really quite amazed when they saw the movie they even
figured out what version it was and things like that and so it actually
triggered a series of follow-on scenes that used actual real hacking software
n map hacking software so I don't know if we've got a URL for this or not
whatever I URL I come up with even the one the end map people come up with
whatever it is it goes away because of copyright but you can find it because
someone always puts it back up so still no side I don't know what they're doing
but they only got two minutes left
so basically the application layer is a rich place
and there's lots of things that happen in the application layer we have this
pipe abstraction it's kind of like a string with two tin cans and we can
shout into one end and stuff comes out the other end later we'll talk about
adding security to that and we use these port numbers to allow to multiple
different servers or services on a computer that we can connect to so we've
kind of now reached the top of the architecture of the internet we've
talked about ethernet the link layer and fiber and all the diverse wireless all
the wonderful things that happen there the internet work layer which is this
kind of geographical hopping thing it's unreliable the TCP layer that
retransmits automatically if necessary and then the application layer which is
what we do with all this networks it's really impressive that this came out of
research work from the 1970s and that most of the architectures that were
really present most the ideas the architecture from the 70s are really
still present with us today as the NSF net came out these architectures evolved
a little bit the last few tweaks and there have been tweaks going on ever
since but the really the last few critical tweaks happened in the late 1980s
the the number of web hosts or the number of hosts on the internet goes
from 6 in 1969 to sort of a billion in 2011 and and it's pretty impressive that
roughly the same architecture that was designed with six computers is still
mostly functioning in mostly the same patterns all these years later with the
billions of computers and so if you start looking at the network now it
almost looks like a live creature with veins and nerves and and it's sort of
almost pulses and you'd see things like you can search on the internet for how
the internet reacted to Hurricane Sandy when like New York City was just like
shut off for three days you know that just kind of like routed around it yeah
a lot of stuff went across the Atlantic Ocean from New York City and yeah I had
found different paths and you know yeah New York was down but the rest of it
wasn't in many ways pretty amazing and we certainly see other situations where
governments try to shut the internet down by going into the server rooms and
shutting off you know what they think is the only connections but then more
connections pop up and so it's it's very much a almost a living thing it's
billions of computers and hundreds of thousands of routers and and it's
hundreds of millions of simultaneous connections going on all the time
including the one we're doing right now probably and it's trillions of bytes of
data moving across and it's it's it's not perfect it but it kind of works you
can think of it as like the largest energy collective engineering thing that
we've done together is humanity we built this it's all one thing and yet it's so
many different pieces and we just kind of keep gluing them together and gluing
more things on more things and it was it really was created almost like life
itself it's very organic it's designed to heal itself rather than be perfect
because things that try to be perfect are fragile and they break too easily but
things that are designed to heal can heal and you're never perfectly correct
you're never all the way up and you're never all the way down and so that's
what's interesting about the internet oops put the wrong way and so we kind of
come to the end of this where we started out with like machines and pulleys and
gears and spraying oil at Bletchley Park and typing a few characters on a
keyboard to this thing where we sort of just take for granted that we can watch
basketball anywhere on the planet just with a couple of swipes of the of the
key and and in a sense it's just that same human urge to communicate at a
distance and so the last thing that I'll close with is another video from Van
Jacobson now this is about a technique he calls content centric networking and
not everybody agrees with Van Jacobson on this you can ask people and they'll
say that's a good idea that I don't present this as the future I present
this more to get you thinking that there is a future that might be different than
the present that what I just told you that seems seems like oh it's perfect
and the and when in this surf in 1969 he figured this out and it was the perfect
thing right and the answer is it might not be and we as engineers and we as the
people of the internet we must understand that in 20 years it might be
all different because 20 years ago it was all different and 30 years before
that it was different yet again and so nothing's perfect and so we should never
be complacent and assume that what we have is trivial or perfect or even the
right answer social we should continue to question and so it's really
interesting to hear again from Van Jacobson who sort of did this great
innovation in 1987 that saved us and yet he thinks that these are issues and
there are issues that need to be saved again and I think in many ways he's right
the question is not so much whether he's right or wrong the question is what will
the ultimate solution that we pick be produced so so take a look at Van
Jacobson and what he can what he is thinking about as terms of the issues in
the future that we're going to need to solve when he talks about content
centered networking